This exercise task is about properties of
Petri nets, and we have been given two reachability
graphs for Petri nets so we do not have the
actual Petri nets in one and two but only
their reachability graphs.
But nevertheless, we are able to decide on
whether some properties are valid
for the Petri nets.
Especially when we have given the information
that there are four transitions for each Petri
net.
We know that within the original Petri
nets, there are four transitions but we
do not know the actual Petri nets.
Let us consider all these properties.
For the actual task, you have to fill in the
properties below, so whether they're valid
or not, but also indicate the reasons why
these properties hold or do not hold.
I will not write down the actual properties.
I would just indicate to properties within
this table here.
But I will talk about the reasons why
I fill in the table the way I'll do.
Let's have a look at the first Petri net and
the first property, which is strongly live.
It does look like that we can reach all the
states within the reachability graph, and
so
this Petri net or the Petri net belonging to
this reachability graph is probably strongly
live.
And we can check if first of all, that we
can reach all the nodes from each node and
as we have a cycle here, it is possible.
So that's the first reason that this strongly
live can reach all the nodes from each other.
And the second part which we have to check
is that all the transitions are within the
reachability graph, because then we can fire
all the transitions as well.
We just choose one state in the reachability
graph.
Let's choose (0,1,1).
So the starting state.
So, when we choose this marking, then we know,
when we have this marking in the Petri
net.
We can fire t4, t1, and t3.
And now we have to check only that we can
also fire t2 when we start from this marking.
And yes, we can.
When we start from this marking, we can fire
t3 and then we can fire t2.
And then we fired these transitions.
We can fire all four transitions when we started
this marking and that's why this is strongly
live.
Now check the second Petri net.
If this is strongly live as well.
In this case, we have four places as we can
see here, there are tokens given for four
places, and again we have these four transitions,
as it was mentioned in the task, and now is
this strongly live.
Well, as we have such a node here where it
seems that it is not strongly live.
Well, what we do we have to check?
Well, we have to check that we can reach another
node from this one and well, we cannot.
We cannot reach all the nodes from each other,
that's why this one is not strongly live.
Not strongly live for the second one.
Let's check if this maybe is weakly live,
although it is not strongly live.
And for this property, we check if
the reachability graph contains all the transitions.
We have t1 in the reachability graph.
We check the reachability graph if it contains
all the transitions.
And we have t1, t2, t3 and t4 within the reachability
graph.
The underlying Petri net would be weakly live
as we can fire all the transitions.
And the other Petri net for this one holds
the same.
We can also check here for all the transitions
t1 to t4, as there four transitions t1, t2
t3, and t4 are within the reachability graph.
This one is weakly live.
Now we can check for deadlock freeness.
And as we’ve already mentioned, we can get
to each of the other nodes when we follow
the edges in the reachability graph.
We suggest that
it is deadlock free.
And then we check just the nodes.
If there is a node where there is no outgoing
edge, and for this node, we have this edge.
For this node, we have this edge.
For this node, we have this outgoing edge.
And for this node, we have this outgoing edge.
Of course, there are more outgoing edges,
but these are just the examples.
For each node we found an outgoing edge, so
we know this one is deadlock free.
Now we check the second net and there we find
a node which has no outgoing edge, so
(0,2,0,0) has no outgoing edge.
This one is actually a deadlock.
This one is not deadlock free.
Now we check for safeness.
Is this net safe?
When is it safe?
It is if there is at most one token for every
place.
When we find any node in the reachability
graph where there's more than one token for
a place, it is not safe.
And in this case, we have, for example, this
node here (0,2,0,0) which contains more
than one token and for the second place, so
there are two tokens and two is greater than
one.
In fact, this is not safe and we can check
the
other Petri net for the same thing.
So now we check in one, and when we look at
this Petri net and we see that this one has
the same properties.
For instance, this node here contains two
tokens in the first place.
So (2,0,0) contains more than one token for the
first place here.
In this case, this is not safe as well.
Now we check bounded, is this Petri net bounded?
Well, we can find a constant C for each of
the tokens of the places where no node has
more tokens than this constant for these cases.
If we can, then it is bounded.
If we choose two for instance, or even
three, well two is enough in this case, or
if we choose C equals two, then we find no
node, which contains more tokens than two.
And because when we check all these numbers
here, we have only 0s, 1s and 2s
for all these nodes in the reachability graph
so in fact this is bounded.
And then we check the second net and here
again, we can choose a constant C equal to two,
it can be the same as in this case, because there
two is the highest number of tokens for a
place here for this Petri net, so in the reachability
graph
there is no number higher than two ever occurring
for any tokens in any place.
And that's why this one is bounded as well.
And then we are done with the task and have
decided all the properties.